William Eastlake papers, 1929-1997
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
William Eastlake papers, 1929-1997
MS 383
Eastlake, William.
This collection consists of the papers of William Eastlake. Articles, book reviews, manuscripts, and photographs are either by or about William Eastlake. The articles contained in this collection are primarily short stories Eastlake contributed to various periodicals, but also included are articles about Eastlake from various newspapers and periodicals. The collection also contains clippings of book reviews for Eastlake's books, as well as many handwritten manuscripts for Eastlake's short stories and books. Miscellaneous materials primarily include announcements and programs for Eastlake's lectures, book publishers' catalogs, and a calendar. The photographs in this collection are primarily of William Eastlake, but also included are photographs of his ranch in New Mexico and various other individuals.
5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
William Eastlake was a writer who was born on July 14, 1917. He grew up in New Jersey during the Great Depression, and following high school he hitchhiked across the country. Eastlake enlisted in the US Army in 1942. He served in the Infantry for four and a half years, and was wounded while leading a platoon during the Battle of the Bulge. Following the war, Eastlake spent several years in Europe. After returning from Europe in the 1950s, Eastlake settled on a ranch in New Mexico. He wrote many short stories and novels about New Mexico and the Southwest including Go in Beauty, The Bronc People, Portrait of an Artist with Twenty-six Horses, and Dancers in the Scalp House.
Eastlake also worked as a correspondent in 1968 in Vietnam for The Nation, and wrote several war novels including Castle Keep, The Bamboo Bed, and The Long Naked Descent into Boston. In addition to his novels, Eastlake was a lecturer at the University of Arizona, the University of New Mexico, and the University of California. He also contributed many short stories to periodicals, including New Mexico Quarterly, Harper's, and Evergreen Review.
Organization
This collection is organized into five
Series I: Articles, 1947-1997
Series II: Book Reviews, 1956-1997
Series III: Manuscripts, 1945-1984
Series IV: Miscellaneous Materials and Text Book Appearances, 1962-1991
Series V: Photographs, 1929-1984
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the papers of William Eastlake. Articles, book reviews, manuscripts, and photographs are either by or about William Eastlake. The articles contained in this collection are primarily short stories Eastlake contributed to various periodicals, but also included are articles about Eastlake from various newspapers and periodicals. The collection also contains clippings of book reviews for Eastlake's books, as well as many handwritten manuscripts for Eastlake's short stories and books.
Miscellaneous materials primarily include announcements and programs for Eastlake's lectures, book publishers' catalogs, and a calendar. The photographs in this collection are primarily of William Eastlake, but also included are photographs of his ranch in New Mexico and various other individuals.
Access Terms
Eastlake, William--Archives.
Short stories, American -- 20th century.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.
Western Stories.
West (U.S.) -- In literature.
American literature -- Southwestern States.
American fiction -- 20th century.
New Mexico -- Fiction.
Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Fiction.
Container List
- Series I: Articles, 1947-1997
  - Essai: "Ishimoto's Land", Summer 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accent: "Little Joe", Autumn 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Hudson Review: "Two Gentlemen from America", Autumn 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Harper's Magazine: "The Medicine Man", March 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harper's Magazine: "The Quiet Chimneys", May 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Américas: "The Chrome Covered Wagon", July 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harper's Magazine: "The Bandits", September 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Collier's: "Where the Warriors Crossed", August 3, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Hudson Review: "The Unhappy Hunting Grounds", Autumn 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harper's Magazine: "Flight of the Circle Heart", November 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Saturday Evening Post: "Man Trap", March 29, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Evergreen Review: "Portrait of an Artist with Twenty-six Horses", Summer 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Nation: "The Navajo and the Barfly", September 12, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Evergreen Review: "Three Heroes and a Clown", December 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction: "What Nice Hands Held", January 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harper's Magazine: "A Bird on the Mesa", October 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Evergreen Review: "Something Big is Happening to Me", July 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Literary Cavalcade: "In a While Crocodile", October 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review: "A Long Day's Dying", Winter 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - New Mexico Quarterly: "The Novels of William Eastlake", Summer 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Critical Study of Eastlake's Novels Featured", Summer 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Argosy: "A Long Day's Dying", December 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Nation: "Hooligans and Indians", January 3, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Harper's Magazine: "There's a Camel in my Cocktail", April 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - The Nation: "The Night We Bombed Peking", July 4, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Evergreen Review: "Jack Armstrong in Tangier", August 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Nation: "Alone on an Elephant", August 22, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Nation: "Dragon Train to Singapore", September 26, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Nation: "To Die in Vietnam", October 24, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Book Week: "The Forked-Tongue Syndrome", January 29, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Nation: "The View from Pancho's Villa", October 2, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The Nation: "Our Lord in Vietnam", November 13, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Nation: "Death of Seven Zipperheads", November 20, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Evergreen Review: "The Last Frenchman in Fez", December 1967 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Nation: "Lost in Vietnam", December 4, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Nation: "Like a Small Dead Man", January 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - The Nation: "Three Purple Hearts, Two Turtle Doves and an Ambush in a Flame Tree", January 22, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Book World: "Great White Father Go Home", February 18, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The Nation: "The Vietnam Dead", February 26, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Atlantic: "The Biggest Thing Since Custer", September 1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Evergreen Review: "Now Lucifer is Not Dead", November 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - New Mexico Quarterly: "The Message", Winter 1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Evergreen Review: "The Hanging at Prettyfields", February 1969 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - (Publication Unknown): "UA's New Resident Writer Admits Ability", August 13, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - The Bulletin: "William Eastlake excited about film of his novel - but won't see it", August 19, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Evergreen Review: "The Bamboo Bed", September 1969 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The Nation: "Whitey's on the Moon Now", September 15, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Argosy: "The Secret of the War", October 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Arizona Daily Wildcat: "Writer Eastlake Ventures into the Artistic Fiber", October 3, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - New Mexico Quarterly: "Dead Man's Guide to Mallorca", Winter 1969 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Sage: "Interview with William Eastlake", Winter 1969 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Southwest Writer's Series: "William Eastlake", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Evergreen Review: "The Dancing Boy", December 1970 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - The Nation: "Seven Firefights in Vietnam", January 11, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Western Review: "William Eastlake: Portrait of the Artist as Shaman", Spring 1971 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Skyline: "Whites say Navajos have no Sacred Shrines", May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Les Lettres Nouvelles: "Pancho et sa villa", September 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cosmopolitan: "The Death of Sun", October 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - South Dakota Review: "Writing about the West", Autumn 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Atlantic Monthly: "Smoke", November 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Penthouse: "Dancers in the Scalp House", December 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Viva: "Last Tango in Gallup", June 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ms.: "Coyotes Love Me", September 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sports Illustrated: "Today is Joy to their World", September 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Genesis: "Music on the Painted Bird", December 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Genesis: "The Naked Bike", March 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sports Illustrated: "Booktalk", May 12, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - South Dakota Review: "William Eastlake", Autumn 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mountain Gazette: "That's Emory Kolb", November 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ms.: "Mrs. Gage in her Bed of Pain with a Nice Cup of Gin", March 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Critique: "Absurdity and Oppositions in William Eastlake's Southwestern Novels", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - South Shore: "Don't Be Afraid, The Clown's Afraid Too", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mule Mountain Observer: "Comparing Russian Invasions of Afghanistan and Czechoslovakia", Jan. 23, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mule Mountain Observer: "Death Tastes Like Real Coffee", Feb. 6, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mule Mountain Observer: "When All the Young in Arizona are Sleeping in a Hotel in Montreal", March 5, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Mule Mountain Observer: "We Must Rage, Rage Against the Dying of the Light", March 14, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bisbee Mountain Journal: "Why and How Billy Killed Jimmy", August 7, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bisbee Mountain Journal: "Watchers of the World Unite - You have Nothing to Gain but your Brains", August 21, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mule Mountain Observer: "Interview with Author-Journalist William Eastlake", Nov. 13, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Perhaps its time to change the way we're brought up", Dec. 22, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Herald Dispatch and Bisbee Review: "Novelist William Eastlake Talks of Ranching, Writer's Wrongs", Nov. 15, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bisbee Times: "One Man's Hero is Another Man's Terrorist", February 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bisbee Times: "Inside the Belly of the Whale", March 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bisbee Times: "The View from Pancho's Villa", May 1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "A Few Words of Protest Before the Ultimate Silence", Dec. 4, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fiction International: "Forum: Writing on Politics", 1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The Small-Towner: "Elderberry Blood", Spring 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Fiction International: "A Tale of the Alhambra", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Letters to the Editor", 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "William Eastlake", May 12, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Ronald Reagan goes ahead -for the Tech of it", January 2, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Los Angeles Times: "Ian Paisley: An 'Ambassador in Bonds' Speaks out Boldly", June 1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Myth-information Will Bring Orwell Back from the Grave", December 21, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Bring Back Gorbie for Demo Ticket", August 6, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Bisbee Magazine: "William Eastlake: Portrait of an Artist with One Dog", Spring 1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Albuquerque Journal Magazine: "The Death of Sun", March 8, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - City Magazine: "Mecham Scuttlebutt in the People's Republic", March 1988 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - (Publication Unknown): "The Best Walls are Built Within", March 2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Why Women Won't Vote for George", July 15, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The Taos Review: "The Writer as a Young Man", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - REAL West: "Red Muslims and Uncle Tomahawks", Spring 1991 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Sierra Vista Herald Dispatch: "Local Author Attends Smithsonian Session", August 25, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - The Journal: "Prettyfields", Spring/Summer 1992 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Headwaters Review: "Books Forge Axes for the Frozen Seas Inside Us", November 1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Rush on Rush", March 30, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "When Times are Hard, Become a Downsizer", June 1994 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Classlessness still persists", May 15, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Eastlake was an Original as Writer, Teacher", July 6, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Albuquerque Journal: "War Coverage Lacking, Author Feels", No Date (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Author William Eastlake Dies", No Date (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Christian 'Beast' Symbolizes our Society's Lack of Options", No Date (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Crossing the Continent at 20 m.p.h.", No Date (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Arizona Daily Star: "Even Today, Jefferson would Believe in the People", No Date (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Interview with Eastlake -America: Nation of Intruders", No Date (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Republicanitis: When you know you show the symptoms", No Date (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - (Publication Unknown): "Shoah is required viewing for the intolerant", No Date (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Series II: Book Reviews, 1956-1997
  - Book Reviews, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Book Reviews, 1966-1997 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Series III: Manuscripts, 1945-1984
  - Autobiography, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #2, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #1, No Date (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #3, No Date (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #3, No Date (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #A, No Date (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Bamboo Bed: Notebook #B, No Date (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Bamboo Bed, No Date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Bamboo Bed, No Date (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Bamboo Bed, also includes Child's Garden of Verses for the Revolution, Morocco, and Castle Keep film revisions, No Date (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Castle Keep: Correspondence and Clippings, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Castle Keep: Movie Script, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Castle Keep, No Date (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Castle Keep, No Date (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Castle Keep, No Date (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Castle Keep, also includes part of Bronc People, No Date (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - A Child's Garden of Verses for the Revolution, No Date (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - A Child's Garden of Verses for the Revolution, No Date (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - A Child's Garden of Verses for the Revolution, also includes partial script for Portrait of an Artist with 26 Horses, No Date (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, No Date (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, also includes Canterbury Tales, No Date (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, also includes Canterbury Tales, No Date (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, also includes The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Dancers in the Scalp House, also includes Portrait of an Artist with 26 Horses script, No Date (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - First two unpublished stories, including "Fort Ord is My Mother, My Wonderful, Beautiful Mother" and "The Soul of an Artist Among the Submarines", No Date (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Go In Beauty galley, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Go In Beauty, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Immortal television script, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Long Naked Descent into Boston, No Date (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Prettyfields, No Date (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Short Stories - Travel, No Date (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Materials and Text Book Appearances, 1962-1991
  - Miscellaneous materials, including announcements, programs, publisher's catalogs, and a calendar, 1970-1991, No Date (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Text Book Appearances, 1962-1986 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series V: Photographs, 1929-1984
  - Photographs of William Eastlake, his ranch in New Mexico and various individuals, 1929-1984, No Date (Box 4, Folder 24)